The recent drop in sound quality is understandable.
最近的声音差一点是情有可原
I've been using my phone to record everything.
都是在用手机在拍啊
I'm currently in Beijing,
因为人也在北京
and haven't returned to Hangzhou.
没有回杭州
So, my G-Nan is not with me.
然后这样我的G难也不在手里啊
Please bear with me, everyone.
大家那个原谅我啊
The volume will be a bit lower recently.
最近的这个声量会比较小一点
But I'll try to turn up the sound in post-production.
但是我会在后期的时候尽量把声音调大
And recently, I've been slicing videos.
然后最近就是切片
Both groups are already full.
两个群已经都满了
I plan to launch the third group at noon today.
今天中午12点准备放第三个群啊
Slicing videos is about to make a big move.
切片是要搞点大事
Because I'm preparing for the publication of a book recently.
因为最近在这个准备书要出版了啊
Three books will be published in succession.
连续出版三本书呃
Slicing videos on a certain platform is used for selling books.
切片在某音是用来这个卖书的
And if you join us,
然后如果你加入的话
selling books now comes with very generous commissions.
现在卖书有非常拥丰厚的佣金啊
That means creating links for book slices to sell.
也就是说做了切片挂书的链接
It's a highly profitable venture.
非常赚钱的一件事情
So everyone, let's get on board early.
然后大家呢早上车啊
Start making money early. Achieve financial freedom. Even if it’s a bit short of the goal, earning ten thousand or so shouldn’t be a big issue, right? This item was previously under a licensing agreement.
早赚钱啊 实现财富自由啊 虽然差那么一点点 但是呢挣个万把块钱应该是不是大问题啊 这个东西因为以往的切片是有授权的
Now that the licensing period has expired,
现在授权期已经过了
everyone can freely create these slices.
大家现在可以自由的做这切片
Of course, there are no restrictions on creating slices for Bilibili.
当然做B站切片没有任何的限制呃
When you create a slice,
你做切片来讲
include the book's link,
挂书的链接
which is typically the most convenient method for optimization.
通常来讲的话是一种最方便的一个优化的方法
In other words,
也就是说
if you participate in the slicing tutorial in our group,
如果你通过这次咱们这个切片群的一个教学啊
You'll get your first account.
你就会获得首先一个账号
And you know, promoting products.
然后你也知道带货啊
Whether it's live streaming or video marketing,
这个甭管直播带货还是视频带货
you'll understand the process.
这个流程是怎么回事
You'll be clear on it.
你也能够清楚
This way, you'll embark on the path of self-employment.
这样就走上了自主创业的道路
And it's even a zero-cost venture.
哎这还是零成本创业
So there's no loss for you.
所以对你来讲没有什么任何的损失
It just takes some time.
就是花一些时间啊
Let's start with a marketing promotion for everyone.
这个给大家先做一个营销推广
Then, in the next four episodes,
然后接下来的四期的这个这个
we'll be chatting about the sheets,
这个这个这个床单聊天呢
I want to talk about the path of rebellion.
我要说的一个叛逆之路啊
This is the first episode on the journey to rebellion.
这个走向叛逆是第一期啊
It covers the story of a prodigal son's comeback.
讲的这个逆子的逆袭之路啊
There are four episodes in total. First, we'll discuss a particular MENTALITY. We're not talking about achieving great fortune at the age of sixty. That's not what I meant. Of course, Comrade Zhang Jiao, in the long river of history,
一共有四期啊 首先来讲咱们还讲的是一种METALITY 咱们讲的不是说让你这个岁在甲子天下大吉 不是说那个意思啊 当然来讲张角同志在这个历史的长河当中啊
has always been regarded as a bandit.
一直被认为是贼寇
This is also a somewhat unfair assessment.
这也是一种呃有失这个公允的
This method of evaluation,
这种这个评判的方法啊
because the biggest bandit in the Three Kingdoms was actually Liu Zhang,
因为三国里边最大的贼其实是刘璋啊
and people like Liu Biao.
刘表这样的人
Zhang Jiao was truly more of a religious leader,
张角真是其实当个教主
and so were Jiping and Yu Ji.
像吉平也是就是这个于吉也是
No matter what
就是他无论怎么样
Actually, if he didn’t stir up trouble
其实他如果不出来搞事的话
He could have lived longer
其实能活的更久
But he had no choice but to cause trouble
但是他没有办法只能出来搞事了啊
Why am I talking about this rebellious spirit
我为什么要讲这个叛逆的这个精神呢
Rebellion starts with yourself
叛逆的精神首先是嘴对着你自己
Not against society
不是说对着社会
Or against the whole
或者说对着那个那个整个的这个这个
Or the overall trend, that’s not what it means
这个这个什么说天下大势不是这个意思
And embarking on a path of rebellion starts with defying yourself.
而说走上叛逆之路是要首先背叛你自己啊
It's not about betraying your conscience.
不是说背叛良心
Nor is it about becoming antisocial.
也不是让你反社会
It's about challenging traditional beliefs,
而是对传统观念
and the self-imposed constraints you have. Taking the road less traveled, indeed. Speaking of the underdog rising, the underdog often ends up with a great outcome. Think about the earliest rebels.
对你自己的一种规劝的一种 走上离经叛道之路啊 咱们说这个逆子逆袭 通常来讲逆子会有很好的结局啊 你想最早的一帮逆子啊
Sailed towards the North American continent
航向了北美大陆
And eventually established a new nation
最后建立了一个新的国家啊
Resisted the British Empire
反抗大英帝国
Regardless of how we look at it
不管怎么样来讲的话
The outcome for rebels is often positive
逆子最后的结果通常是好的
Because generally speaking
因为通常来讲的话
When we talk about traditional Chinese culture
咱们说中国的传统文化当中啊
We say that Confucianism is the least tolerant of defiance
我们说儒家是最不讲离经叛道的
It emphasizes the hierarchy of ruler and subject, father and son
是讲君臣父子这一套
Just like the song in Black Myth: Wukong says, 'No ruler, no father'
就好像这个黑神话悟空里边唱的这个无君无父
No law and order
无法纪啊
The ruler and father are the law
君父就是法纪
So, when we talk about
所以来讲的话
In the new era
咱们说在新的时代里边
Why do we need to emphasize innovation in our thinking
为什么要讲究思想上的一种革新呢
Because we are now facing a clash of civilizations
因为咱们现在面对的是一种文明的冲突
The clash of civilizations that Huntington talked about
亨廷顿讲的文明的冲突
Now, there are several established civilizations in the world
现在是世界上几大成型的文明
The Chinese civilization has been in opposition to the Western civilization as a whole.
中华文明在跟西方文明这个整个阵营在对抗
So it's a comparison and contest between individuals,
所以是一种人与人
between nations,
国家与国家
and between societies.
社会与社会之间的比较衡量对抗
This includes both hot wars and cold wars.
这其中有热战也有冷战
Many aspects are a test of strength, a competition of lifestyles. We know there are comparisons like the one between Xiaohongshu and its counterparts. But more importantly, We can't be content with the current status quo.
很多东西是一种实力的比拼 是一种生活方式的比拼啊 我们知道有小红书大对照 但更多的来讲的话 我们不能满足于现在的一些的既成事实啊
In many other aspects,
更多的一些方面来讲
our national defense capabilities have improved.
我们现在国防力量上升了
When it comes to our economic structure,
我们在很多的经济结构上面来讲的话
we have our own advantages.
有自己的优势
However, no matter what,
但是无论如何啊
if we don't start from a people-oriented perspective,
如果我们不是从这个人以人为本人出发
we're not suggesting that you become antisocial,
我们说的不是说你走向反社会啊
or that you defy conventional norms.
你这个离经叛道
Then, this traitor to the nation
然后做了这个民族败类
That's not what I meant
不是这个意思
This judgment is about judging oneself from within
这个判是判自己内心里边一个
A judgment based on established norms
约定俗成的规矩的判这种判啊
It's about, for example, if we eventually leave the labor force
是讲你最后比如说我们脱离了这个劳动序列
And get out of the rut of earning a fixed salary
脱离了拿个死工资的这个感觉
And transform into a new entrepreneur
而变成了自己一个新的企业家的
This completes the path of a comeback
这个完成了逆袭之路啊
Betting on the life environment you originally came from
背叛了你原来所在的这个生活环境
This kind of betrayal
这种背叛
So we call this the Quartet of Rebellious Sons
所以我们这个就是叫做逆子四部曲
First, one must head towards rebellion
首先就要走向叛逆
Everyone can see that what's recently popular
大家看其实最近比较火的
For instance, Nezha directed by Jiaozi For example, The Wandering Earth by Guo Fan Like if the name is mispronounced Don't get upset For example, Feng Ji, who specializes in dark kung fu For example, Zhang Yiming from ByteDance
比如说哪吒二饺子 比如说流浪地球郭帆啊 比如说啊名字要是叫错了 别生气啊 比如说黑生化武功的冯骥 比如说你像这个字节跳动的张一鸣
All these people
所有这些人
All of us who have become famous
所有我们这些成成名的这些啊
These entrepreneurs
这些企业家啊
These cultural figures
文化的这些文化人
And how should I put it
还有这些怎么说呢
These cultural creators, in fact
文化创作者这些人其实来讲的话
Firstly, the post-80s are quite happy to be part of the same generation as them
首先八零后挺高兴能跟他们是同一代人
But to be honest, the post-80s have had a tough time
但是八零后说实在的挺倒霉
The rebellious spirit of the 80s generation isn't as strong as that of the 90s and 00s generations.
八零后的叛逆精神没有九零后零零后那么的足
But our generation is the one that started moving towards rebellion.
但是我们这一代是走向叛逆啊
And we are the generation that is moving towards maturity.
走向这个成熟的一代
We, this generation of people,
就是我们这一代人
whether they studied abroad or stayed in China,
很多人甭管是留学的还是在国内的人
are experiencing rapid exchanges of ideas and information.
很多东西都是在快速的交换
The rapid replacement of old knowledge means that,
快速的更替旧有的知识来讲的话
what we learned back then is no longer sufficient for today’s society.
已经不能足以啊用到今天的社会了
For instance, when I went abroad to study,
比如像我当初去留学的时候
In 2007 and 2008
07年零八年
the internet in China was widely seen as declining
那个时候国内的网络是一片唱衰的啊
it was filled with all sorts of negativity all kinds of things, including The Flowers of Evil these were the prevailing views but after 2020 especially in 2024 many things post-pandemic
是一片的各种各样的啊雾霾啊 各种各样什么那个什么那个这个恶之花啊 都是这种论调啊 等到2020年以后 特别是2024年啊 很多东西疫情后啊
have undergone tremendous changes
很多东西发生了翻天覆地的变化啊
Regardless of the public opinion field or people's fundamental thinking
甭管是舆论场还是大家的根本性思维
it's simply a different generation
还是说完全就不是一代人了
the post-70s
七零后
now the post-60s
现在六零后
have already stepped down from the main arena of the public opinion field
他们已经从舆论场的这个主阵营中
they have already stepped down
已经降下来了
it's more about the post-80s now
更多来讲现在是八零后
the post-90s are taking the stage
九零后在唱在上台
taking center stage
在唱戏
We're all in our forties now
都变成40多岁了
In our thirties
30多岁了
So the core demographic of society has shifted
所以来讲社会的中坚人群的年代发生了变化
People's ideologies have also changed
人的意识形态也发生了变化
Nowadays
现在来讲的话
If it used to be slightly to the right of center
如果以前啊说中间偏右的话
Now it's more center-left
现在是更中间更偏左一点
But whether it's more left or more right
但是无论更是偏左还是偏右来讲
From a personal perspective
从个人的角度来讲话
Only personal development
只有个人的发展
setting aside grand narratives
抛开宏大叙事来讲
is what's most beneficial for you
才是对你最有利的
So, let's talk about
所以来讲
we say we want to deviate from a fixed path
我们说我们要离开一条固定的一个路线
To start with
首先来讲的话
what does it mean to take the path of rebellion
走上叛逆之路是指什么呢
it means you shouldn't be a compliant child
是指你不要做一个听话的孩子
don't always listen to your parents Above parents there is something established by usage in society the educational system of society it will guide you and offer advice to mold you into a competent worker
不要什么都听父母的啊 在父母之上 还有一种社会约定俗成的东西 社会的教育系统 他会把你主教就是把你进行规劝 把你培养成一个合格的打工人啊
of course, if you follow the conventional path in society
当然你走一个社会的正常的一个道路的路线
be a good child who listens to your parents
做父母听话的好孩子啊
be a, how should I put it,
做社会的一个怎么说呢
a good citizen
好公民来讲的话
You won't have any problems.
你不会有任何问题
You won't face any issues in this life.
你在这人生当中不会有任何问题
But now, speaking of the current situation,
但是现在来讲的话
what we're facing is,
我们面对的是一个什么呢
even if there's a path, you can't walk it.
现在是有路你也走不了
we're up against this reality.
面对的是这样一个现实啊
For instance, your parents want you to get married.
比如说父母希望你结婚啊
They also want you to have kids early.
父母希望你早生小孩啊
And society expects you to start working early.
然后呢社会希望你早上背
Get a mortgage as soon as possible
早日背上房贷
Get a car loan
背上车贷
Take all the money out of the bank and spend it
把银行里别存钱都他拿出来花掉
Would you then have to take the path of rebellion?
那你是不是就得走上叛逆之路了
Would you listen to their advice?
你就能听他们的规劝吗
Right?
对不对
The Civil Affairs Bureau has a lot to say about many things
民政局暗广很多东西来讲
Could you truly and completely follow their path?
你能够真真正正完完全全的按照他们来的走吗
Not necessarily, let me explain to you
未必为什么我跟你去讲
Let's look at the Wealth of Nations You want to read The Prince Check these out Our Western Jia Xu and Machiavelli How he advises
要看国富论 是你要看君主论 看看这些啊 西方的贾诩马加维利同志 他是怎么样规劝啊
Advises you
规劝你的
How to, how shall I put it
怎么样走上一个怎么说呢
How to cure the nobles
如何去治愈贵族
How to cure the common people
如何去治愈平民老百姓啊
So in my last episode, I mentioned Comrade Musk
所以我上一期就说到马斯克同志
the outcome might be quite tragic
可能最后的结果非常惨啊
considering the historical context in China
因为在中国历史上来看
people like him often ended up tragically
这样的人的结果都非常惨
you can only use one faction of nobles to combat another
你只能用一派贵族去打击另一派贵族
have nobles from one region combat
由一个地方的贵族去打击
nobles from another region
另外一个地方的贵族啊
or nobles from one country defeat those from another country
或者由一个国家的贵族打败另一个国家的贵族
if you completely draw your strength from the common people
如果你完完全全啊从平民当中汲取力量
Then, how do you defeat, well, let's say
然后去击败一个怎么说呢
the existing interest groups?
现有的这个利益集团来讲
The outcome is usually not good.
通常来结果是非常不好
Especially when you use administrative measures.
特别是你用行政手段
Once power is in your hands,
所谓一朝权在手
you might take advantage of it.
便把肋来
You might start issuing orders.
便把那个令来行
But when you don't have authority,
但是你要没有权柄的时候
what are you going to do?
你该怎么办呢
You might end up on the defensive.
啊你很可能就会被反攻
It's like settling old scores.
倒算求后算账
So, what's the root of all this? In our video, we don't mention these things. We don't talk about anti-marriage or anything like that. We're not talking about opposition or confrontation. We focus on the personal level. We discuss how you should break free from your own entrenched mindset. How should you betray your own entrenched way of thinking?
所以这是一切的什么 所以我们的视频里边呢 我们首先不提及这些东西 我们说的也不是什么反婚欲啊 啊走向对立不是这样的东西 我们讲的是从个人层面上 你应该如何啊背叛你自己固有这种思想
We often say that we should listen to our parents' advice.
我们说固有的这种思想要听父母的话
But listening to our parents,
但是听父母的话
we need to understand when it's right to do so.
我们要明白什么情况下听父母的话是对的
For example, if I come from a relatively wealthy background,
比如说我出身的阶级比较富有
a higher social class,
比较高
my parents have arranged many things for me.
父母呢给我安排了很多东西
He is his disciple,
他是他的门生
and his former officials are spread throughout the world.
故吏遍天下
Following the path laid out by our parents
按父母的道路走
Whether I attended an international school or studied abroad
不论是我上国际学校还是出国留学
or stepped into the workforce
还是啊走向工作岗位
my parents paved the way for me
父母给我铺好了路
at that time, my parents had a high level of insight
这个时候父母的认知是高的
I followed their path
我按着他的路走
generally speaking, there wouldn’t be any major issues
通常来讲不会出现大的问题
perhaps I might have been a bit rebellious
也许来讲我可能叛逆一些
my parents wanted me to study finance
父母希望我学金融啊
but I didn’t want to study finance
我不想学金融
I want to study physics
我想学物理
What do my parents expect from me?
父母希望我怎么样呢
Marry someone
跟某个人结婚
I don't want to marry him
我不想跟他结婚
I want to marry a heiress from another industry
我想跟另一个另一个行业的千金结婚啊
As long as you don't casually take it down
只要你不会说随便下架
Typically speaking
那通常来讲的话
Your social status Your income In various situations, there won't be major issues. Many of the people around me are from the post-90s generation. They look for relationships that are well-matched. Or it could be that a golden phoenix has flown out of an ordinary nest.
你的社会等级地位 你的收入啊 那是各种情况的话 不会出现大的问题啊 我现在身边很多九零后啊 人家找的就是门当户对的关系 也可能是自己呢鸡窝里飞出了金凤凤凤凰啊
Or they might be an only child from the Jiangsu-Zhejiang-Shanghai region.
也可能就是本来就是打江浙沪独生女
This kind of issue arises.
出现了这种问题
So when I look at the rich second generation among the post-90s crowd around me,
所以他们啊你看九零后的我身边这帮富二代
the rich second generation tends to marry within their own circle.
富二代找富二代结婚
This is a very common thing.
这是很正常的一件事
But what is the challenge for ordinary people like us?
但是我们普通人面对的问题是什么呢
The issue is that your parents often become an obstacle to your social mobility.
就是你的父母通常是你阶级跃升的阻碍啊
If they don't have money, they won't help you with a down payment.
没钱他给你交一首付
And they leave you on your own afterward.
后边不管你了
If they don't have money, they still insist you go ahead.
没钱非要让你去啊
They push you to buy a house or a car, insisting you get a nice car.
买房贷车贷非要你买一好车
They want to save face.
他得有面子啊
When it comes to parents,
父母来讲的话
Do you have any siblings?
你还有兄弟姐妹
You need to take care of your siblings.
你得照顾兄弟姐妹啊
Your parents insist on buying a house in the county town.
父母他非得要在县城买房啊
Because they don’t think the self-built houses in the countryside are good enough.
因为他不觉得农村的自建房啊
They feel it’s embarrassing.
觉得太丢人了
If I buy a house in the county town, there are many people like that.
我要去县城买房就有很多
Or you might want to go abroad.
这样的人或者你想出国
Or you might want to get married a couple of years later.
或者你想晚两年结婚
Or you might want to marry someone specific.
或者你想嫁给谁
Who you want to marry
想娶谁
or how you are
或者你怎么样
they will try to obstruct you in every way when it comes to such parents you need to rebel you can't just blindly follow your parents we say Chinese people should be filial this concept of loyalty and filial piety take the part about being filial and be cheerful
反正就是各方面给你进行阻碍 这种父母来讲的话 你就要走向叛逆 就是不能完全听父母的 我们说中国人要尽孝心啊 君臣父子这套东西呢 你取其一半就是孝要笑
But don't follow his advice and opinions entirely.
但是不要完全听他的建议和意见
Because when it comes to your parents,
因为你的父母来讲的话
they might be limited by their social class.
很可能会受限于他的阶级啊
For example, my parents,
比如说我的父母啊
I didn’t completely listen to my parents.
我就没有完全听我父母
The social class my parents belong to,
因为我父母所在的阶级
where life is quite comfortable,
生活养尊处优
affects many of their views and perceptions.
他们的很多的观念意识上呢
They might see themselves as ordinary people.
他可能觉得自己是普通人
But in fact, the environment they are in
但实际上他们所处的环境
the people they interact with are not entirely
接触的人不是完完全全
ordinary people
普通人
from the real lower strata of Chinese society
所处的真正的中国底层社会中的那种普通人
that kind of situation
那种状态
so some of their ideas are more idealistic
所以他们有些想法是比较理想化的
more urban
比较城市化的
for example, they hope I take the technical route
比如说他们希望我走上技术路线
hope I can align with their goals soon
希望我早日呢靠拢啊
Going in this direction,
走这个方向来讲的话
becoming someone's lackey,
成为别人的狗腿子
this is the best route my parents gave me,
这是我父母给我的最佳的一个路线
because they think this path is suitable in Beijing's environment, it's appropriate, but the issue is I'm an ENTJ with a strong personality, if you ask me to follow this path, I feel resentful inside,
因为觉得这样的路线在北京的这么一个环境下 是合适的 但问题是我是一个魁罡命的ENTJ啊 你让我去走这样的路线来讲 我心里是不服气的
even quite distressed.
甚至是很难受的
Even at the beginning, I thought I was on the path of a strategist.
甚至我最开始自己也是认为自己是走谋士路线
That should be right.
应该是对的
But later, reality proved that
但是后来事实发现啊
this approach actually limited my development.
这种方式反而限制我的发展
So, to speak,
所以来讲的话
taking the unconventional path,
走上离经叛道之路
not following the route of my parents, both civil servants,
不按你父母的两个事业单位职工的这条路走
might be the right choice.
那可能是对的啊
Many people's parents, to be honest, are
很多人的父母甚至来讲的话是
For example, if you come from the countryside
比如说你从农村里出来
university students may use discriminatory terms
大学生所谓的有歧视性的词汇
like 'small-town test takers'
小镇做题家
their understanding can never surpass yours
他的认知绝对不可能超过你
they simply don't have basic scientific literacy
他根本就不具备基本的科学素养
nor do they have a modern sense of civilization
也不具备一个现代的一个文明
or knowledge of social economics
社会的一个经济知识
their understanding of the West's nearly 300 years
他对西方的三近300年
compared to China's 5000-year history
中华文明上下5000年的历史
He has no idea how politics operates.
也完全不知道政治是怎么样活动的
He is even more clueless about what's going on.
他更不知道怎么回事
He doesn’t understand how society functions.
社会是怎样运作的
He is completely in the dark about it.
他是完全不知道你
You are already the pinnacle of intelligence and experience in your family.
你已经是你家庭智商跟见识的巅峰了
So you should listen to them. You should take the filial piety route. The way of ruler and minister, father and son. You will surely find yourself increasingly isolated. Including many UPloaders around me they encounter some issues
所以你听他们的 你去走孝道路线啊 君臣父子那一套 你肯定会把自己过得越来越抽手 包括我现在身边很多up主 他们身边遇到一些问题
like being pressured to get married during the Spring Festival
就是春节催婚啊
or being urged to have children, even though they've already made it as UPloaders
催婚催生明明都已经做到up主了
but their parents hope they’ll come home and provide for the family
却希望他回家口供啊
they have no idea how much you earn
父母根本不知道你挣多少钱
or what your current social status is
根本不知道你现在的社会地位是什么
or what the current social reality is
根本不知道现在的社会现实是什么
and then they force you to take on loans
然后呢强行让你背贷款啊
When house prices have already started to decline,
在房价已经开始下行的时候
it’s asking you to buy a ready-made house,
让你去买现成的房子
which is simply courting disaster.
这简直就是作死啊
In China, only the top 20 cities
中国的房子只有排名前20名的城市
have the agglomeration effect,
具有虹吸效应啊
where property prices won’t plummet.
那些房价是不会大跌的
But let’s not even talk about the county towns.
但是县城咱就别说了
Alright,
好吧
we’re in 2025 now.
咱们都到这时候都2025年了
Let's not talk about the housing demand in the county still not being met.
咱就别再说县城的房子还供不应求呢
Alright?
好不好
Isn't that right?
是不是
Who are we trying to fool?
那能骗得了谁啊
So, in many cases,
所以很多的时候来讲
if you want to achieve financial independence,
如果你想走上经济上的独立
if you want to achieve true independence in society,
你想走上啊这个社会意义上的真正的独立
you first need to take a path of rebellion.
首先就要走上一条叛逆之路
Rebellion starts with rebelling against yourself. It's about the social class your parents come from This judgment is based on such perceptions You are, in fact, a product of your parents Much of your understanding comes from your parents
叛谁首先判的就是你自己判的 就是你的父母的出身的阶层 判的是这种认知啊 你其实是你父母的造化产物 你很多的认知来自于你的父母
Your parents often directly interfere with you
你的父母直接干涉你
In many cases
很多的时候来讲
They hope you'll be an obedient child
希望你做听话的孩子
But when you are obedient
但是你听话
Ultimately, it maximizes their own interests
最终来讲的话是他们自己的利益最大化啊
Your life is about being chosen, being selected.
你的人生就是被选举被选被被选取
It's a life that has been picked and optimized.
被啊拣选的被优化过的这么一种人生
Because for them,
因为对他们来讲
the fear of death is immense.
对死亡的恐惧是非常大的啊
Having you bear a child
让你生了孩子
ensures their retirement is secure.
自己的退休生活就有着落了
Once you truly have descendants,
自己呢真正有子孙了以后呢
your own benefits can be maximized.
自己来讲利益就能达到最大化
People, relatively speaking,
人相对来讲
You might always say it’s for my own good
其实嘴上总会说我是为你好
but in reality
但是实际上来讲
people are selfish
人都是自私的
you have a selfish and ruthless side too
你也有自私残忍的一面
you also have moments when you neglect your parents
你有也有不顾父母的一面
at the same time
同时来讲
you might have seen some video that
你可能看到了一个什么视频来讲
makes you feel sorry for your parents again
你又啊心疼父母了
but it’s always a constant tug-of-war
但是永远在这种恒长的拉扯之间
Your parents are people like that too.
你的父母也是这样的人
If your parents were really those kids,
如果你父母真是那些孩子
Go ahead and give it your all. Mom and Dad won’t rush you into marriage. They won’t care which city you go to. They won’t mind whether you stay in the country or go abroad. They won’t bother about what major you choose. Then your parents are just like mine. In that case, I suggest you try to be as filial as possible.
放开手干吧 爸爸妈妈也不催你结婚 也不管你去哪个城市 也不管你去国内国外 也不管你选择什么专业 那你的父母跟我的父母一样 那样来讲的话 我建议你就是尽量要孝顺他们
Be kind to them.
要对他们好一点
But never completely follow your parents' advice.
但是但是永远不要完完全全听父母的意见
That's the first step towards rebellion.
这是走向叛逆之路的第一条
Because you need to realize that there's a difference between you and your parents.
就是因为你要知道你跟你的父母已经有差别了
How far you can go in life
你这一辈子能走多远
will determine how far your family can go.
就决定了你的家族能走多远
Regardless of whether you have children or not,
不管你生不生小孩
regardless of whether you get married or not.
不管你结不结婚
You will be the pinnacle of your family in this era.
你将是你家族的这个时代的巅峰
So, when facing a complex and diverse society,
所以在面对一个纷繁复杂的一个社会来讲
you must first embark on a path of rebellion.
首先你就要走上叛逆之路
You need to be the master of your own destiny.
你要做自己的主人
You should step out from the family lineage,
你要从家谱
starting a new branch with your generation.
从你这一代单开一
You need to understand that you will be the peak of your family.
你要明白你将来是你家庭的巅峰
Your family will achieve social mobility through you.
你的家庭因为通过了你完成了阶级跃升
Therefore, the influence of the old family members on you will be minimal.
所以那些旧有的家庭成员对你的影响就不大了
You have, in terms of mindset, already completed the immigration.
你现在从意识上来讲已经完成了移民
You have arrived at the new continent.
你已经来到了新大陆
You have moved to a new city.
来到了新的城市
You have entered a new field.
来到了新的领域
Here, you will be participating in new social competitions. So the help your parents can offer is quite limited. If you live close to them, and have them take care of your children, you will often have to abide by their rules. You might be bound to them for life.
在这个地方参与新的社会竞争 所以你的父母能给你的帮助来讲的话十分有限 如果你一旦跟他们住得近 让他们替你带小孩的话 很多的时候你就要受其限制 你可能一生与其绑定
It’s impossible to completely escape their control.
就不可能完完全全脱离他们的掌控
When you’re young,
在你年轻的时候
you should try to break free from their control as much as possible.
一定要尽量脱离掌控
Because when you reach my age,
因为你到了我这个岁数来讲
your parents’ health may decline,
父母身体不好了
and you’ll need to be there to take care of them.
你就要在身边照顾
This is the filial piety we Chinese value.
这个是咱们中国人的孝道
But if you’re in your twenties or thirties,
但是如果你二三十岁
if you can't escape your parents' control
就脱离不了父母的掌控的话
that's not right
是不对的
returning to your parents' side in your forties or fifties
四五十岁再回到父母身边
that's a more complete process
这个是一种比较完整的一个过程啊
at that time, if you're willing to have children
那个时候你愿意生小孩
if you're willing
你你愿意啊
after achieving a certain level of success
取得一定的成绩以后
if you're willing to stay with your parents
你愿意在父母待在身边
that's your own freedom
那个是你自己的自由
of course
当然来讲
life is full of separations and reunions
人这一辈子分分离离
many times of coming and going
分分合合会要很多次
but if you stay with your parents all the time
但是如果你一直待在父母身边的话
you won't have a significant future
断然没有大的出息啊
so many people can return to their hometown to start a business
所以很多人啊你回乡创业也可以
but if you do it just to be close to your parents
但是如果你为了离父母近
returning to your hometown to start a business
回乡创业
you miss out on the opportunities in big cities
你失去了大城市奋斗的机会
if you start to settle for a comfortable life now
你现在就开始躺平
in many cases, some opportunities
很多的时候来讲一些机会啊
opportunity costs
机会成本
time costs
时间成本
and financial costs
还有金钱成本啊
you won't have them anymore of course, we say life is a journey all roads lead to Rome we often say if your background is relatively low you must understand if you come from a poor family, you should leave home
你就不会再拥有 当然来讲我们说人生之路 条条大路通罗马 我们常说如果你的出身来讲的话 比较低的话 一定要明白啊 家贫走他乡啊
if your father is weak, go into business
足忘刘渊吉哈
if your mother is weak, go into business
母弱出商
if your father is strong, become an official
贾父强
so I've been telling you
所以早就跟你们说
starting a business is your only path
创业是你唯一的路
moving to a big city is your only path
走向大城市是你唯一的路
only by moving to a big city
你只有走向了大城市
becoming a pioneer in an industry
走向了一个行业的发起者
a content creator
一个内容的创作者啊
an asset owner
一个资产的拥有者
can you truly rise above your current class
你才能真正脱离你目前的阶级
in terms of assets
从资产上的意义来讲
in terms of income
从你的收入的意义上来讲
you truly become a new asset class
真正变成了一个新的资产阶级
you can stand firm in a modern commercial society
你才能在一个现代商业社会中立足
because in a modern commercial society
因为现代社会商业社会中
no matter what
无论怎么样啊
no matter how ideology changes
意识形态怎么样
how the structure of the country differs
国家的构成方式不一样
our economic conditions
但是我们的经济状况
the laws governing our economic society
我们的经济社会运行的规律
are the same worldwide
全世界都是一样的
so to take the lead in the economic society
所以你要在经济社会中取得头筹
you must take the path of turning things around
你就必须走上逆袭之路
that is, being a rebel taking the path of rebellion is the correct start to your life
也就是说做一个逆子 走向了叛逆之路 是你一生的正确的开始